Litchfield Female Academy Collection
Litchfield Historical Society
- Student Papers, Records, and Documents
  - Waterman, Delia (Storrs) Mrs. Thomas T., 1822 Aug 3 (Folder 85)
    Transcript of letter from Delia Storrs to her half brother Lucius Storrs of Buffalo, NY while Delia was at the Litchfield Female Academy. Folder includes a letter from Mrs. Jason Waterman, who sent the copy of Delia's letter, dated 22 Mar 1935 from Washington, D.C. to Mrs. George Maynard Minor, with information about Delia Storrs and her family.
  - Wells, Jane (Vanderburgh), Mrs. John, 1822 (Folder 86)
    Album of pencil drawings and watercolors
  - Wells, Julia Ann (Walsh), Mrs. Charles, 1828-1829 (Folder 87)
    Photocopies and transcripts of 8 letters between Julia Ann Walsh and her family while she was at LFA. Includes her father & mother Henry and Mehetable Walsh, brother William B. Walsh, and friend Louisa in Litchfield.
  - Wells, Julia Ann (Walsh), Mrs. Charles, 1837-1840 (Folder 88)
    Photocopies of 6 letters to Julia Ann Walsh in Newburgh (NY) from her brothers Abraham, Andrew, and James Walsh; and cousin Mehetable.
  - Whiting, Sarah (Clark), Mrs. Jason, 1825 (Folder 89)
    Photocopies and transcripts of 3 letters from Sarah in Litchfield to her cousin Sophia Griswold.
  - Whiting, Sarah (Clark), Mrs. Jason, 1826 (Folder 90)
  - Whiting, Sarah (Clark), Mrs. James, 1817-1837 (Folder 91)
  - Whittlesey, Maryann (Bacon), Mrs. Chauncey, 1802 (Folder 92)
    "Maryann Bacon's Journal written the 15 year of her age 1802" - diary and notebook including lyrics to songs. Also a handwritten copy of a British song with the first line "Arise arise Britannia's sons arise"
  - Woodruff, Henrietta Sophorina (Seymour), Mrs. George C., 1823 Oct (Folder 93)
    Litchfield Female Academy diploma, Oct. 1823
  - Bassett, Mary, 1823-1832 (Folder 94)
    Album - compositions, poetry, etc.
  - Bassett, Mary, 1832 (Folder 95)
    Autograph album inscribed "To Miss Mary Bassett, presented by her affectionate pupils, Eliza Lewis, Mary Brittin, Hannah Hoskins, Maria Beach, Caroline Seymour, Harriet Seymour, Elizabeth Choate. Auburn, Sept. 25th 1832." Mary Bassett was a pupil at LFA 1823-1824 and later became a teacher.
  - Beckwith, Jane M. (Seymour), Mrs. Josiah, 1822-1827 (Folder 96)
    Autograph album. Jane Maria Seymour was a LFA student 1822-1828.
  - Buel, Mary, 1831-1841 (Folder 97)
    Autograph album. Mary Buel was a LFA student 1826-1831.
  - Flewwelling, Julia (Canfield), Mrs.Samuel, 1850 (Folder 98)
    Notebook, circa 1850, with copies of literary works. Includes an index in the back. Julia Canfield was a LFA student circa 1814.
  - Garrett, Margaret C (Bolles), Mrs. Joshua, 1824-1827 (Folder 99)
    Autograph album 1824-1827 with notes to 1851. Margaret Bolles was a LFA student 1816-1821.
  - Hart, Jennette Margaret, 1819 (Folder 100)
    Album of poetry. Jennette Margaret Hart was an LFA student in 1819.
  - Houston, Hannah, 1818-1819 (Folder 101)
    School notebook - "Lectures on Natural Philosophy". Hannah Houston was an LFA student in 1818-1819.
    Includes a transcript.
  - Mansfield, Mary (Peck), Mrs. Edward D., 1825-1826 (Folder 102)
    Autograph album inscribed: "Mary W. Peck from Edward D. Mansfield Jan. 1, 1825." Includes art work, hair memorials, and many inscriptions including the Beechers and Wolcotts. Mary Wallace Peck was an LFA student 1811-1816, and later became a teacher there.
  - Seymour, Delia, 1818-1832 (Folder 103)
    School notebook, autograph album, and diary. Includes botany lecture notes. Delia Storrs Seymour was an LFA student in 1818-1821
  - Seymour, Delia, 1829-1833 (Folder 104)
    Autograph album. Delia Seymour was an LFA student 1816-1821.
  - Stevens, Jane (Wadhams), Mrs. Henry W, 1829-1831 (Folder 105)
    Autograph album. Jane Wadhams was an LFA student 1830-1832.
  - Williams, Catherine, 1830-1836 (Folder 106)
    Autograph album. Catherine Williams was an LFA student in 1830.
- Pierce Family Papers
  - Brace, Emma P, 1843 Apr 19 (Folder 1)
    Testimonial from Hartford Female Seminary that she is entitled to First Rank in Senior Class. Signed by J.P. Brace.
  - Brace, James, 1811 (Folder 2)
    Two letters dated 1811 Mar 14 and 1811 Apr 2 from Litchfield (Conn) to his son John P. Brace in Williamstown (Mass) with information about school costs and advice to John about maintaining his health.
  - Brace, James P, 1847 Jul 10 (Folder 3)
    Letter from J.P. Brace in New Milford to Solomon Porter inquiring about finding for place for his youngest son James in Porter's business. Also whether there is employment for J.P. Brace in a proposed Hartford high school.
  - Brace, John P, 1829 Dec 21 (Folder 4)
    Address delivered before the Temperance Society of Litchfield (Conn.)
  - Brace, Jonathan & Brace, Frances Ann, 1815-1822 (Folder 5)
    [Correspondence] Photocopies of letters from Jonathan Brace 1815 Oct 24 and 1818 Oct 21 to his granddaughter Frances Ann in Hartford; and 1822 Jul 24 and 1822 Oct 15 from Hartford to Frances Ann in Litchfield. Two letters from Frances Ann to her grandparents dated 3 June 1822 and 1822 Aug 15 from Litchfield whilte she was a student at Miss Pierce's School.
  - Brace, Susannah (Pierce), Mrs. James, 1811-1814 (Folder 6)
    Four letters from Litchfield (Conn) to her son John Pierce Brace in Williamstown (Mass) with news of family and friends.
  - Croswell, Ruth Pierce, 1899 Aug (Folder 7)
    Typed transcript of a newspaper article "Two Memorable Women: Ruth Pierce Croswell" written by Henry Brace, New York August 1899.
    Handwritten notes about members of the Pierce/Croswell family.
  - Croswell, Thomas, 1792 May 31 (Folder 8)
    Letter from New York to Ruth Pierce Croswell (Mrs. Thomas) with news of his travels.
  - Loring, Anna (Brace), Mrs. Charles, 1818 Aug 3 (Folder 9)
    Letter from Boston to her brother John P. Brace in Litchfield with general news and inquiring about Litchfield and his lady friends.
  - Pierce, James, 1813 Jul 21 (Folder 10)
    Letter to Sally Pierce in Litchfield with a note from Mr. Wilkes requesting his friends in Litchfield find a room for Mr. Bossange, a young gentleman from France.
  - Pierce, Jonathan, 1787 (Folder 11)
    Two letters dated 1781 Jan 4 and 31 Dec from New York to his sister Ruth Pierce.
  - Pierce, Mary (Folder 12)
    Letter dated Litchfield Aug. 19 to Charles G. Loring in Boston with news of friends and family.
  - Pierce, Sarah, 1800-1844 (Folder 13)
    5 letters to Ruth (Pierce) Croswell, Mrs. Thomas, who was Sarah Pierce's sister.
  - Pierce, Sarah. Memorial, 1934 (Folder 14)
    Information about the Sarah Pierce Memorial tablet and boulder dedicated August 13, 1934. Includes documents from The Mary Floyd Tallmadge Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution; a speech by Alain C. White; and history of the memorial.
  - Pierce family, 1752-1803 (Folder 15)
    "Memorandum of John Pierce family" dated 26 Jun 1807.
  - Rogers, Anna P, circa 1829 (Folder 16)
    Letter to Sarah Pierce dated New York Jan. 27 [1829] [note: the year was determined using a perpetual calendar] announcing the birth of a daughter and reminiscencing about Litchfield.
  - Shedden, Julia, 1807 May 13 (Folder 17)
    Letter from Julia Shedden and E. Johnson to Abel and John P. Brace.
- Emily Noyes Vanderpoel Papers
  - Correspondence and Research
    The bulk of this sub-series is the replies sent to Mrs. Vanderpoel in response to her inquiries while researching her book, "Chronicles of a Pioneer School" regarding Litchfield Female Academy students.
    - Alton,Mary Brace, 1902 June 12 (Folder 1)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel replying to ENV's note to her grandmother Brace.
    - Avery,Phebe Augusta Ely (Folder 2)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel with remarks about Caroline Ely who attended Miss Pierce's School.
    - Barnard,Emily, 1900 Sep 25 (Folder 3)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel about trying to find her late father's papers concerning Miss Pierce's School
    - Barnard,Henry, 1879,1897 (Folder 4)
      Two letters to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel from Henry Barnard. One dated Hartford (Conn.)
      1879 Dec 10 requesting information about Miss Pierce's School. The second dated from Hartford (Conn.) 1897 Jul 23 includes a table of contents for a book on schools by Barnard indicating a chapter on Miss Pierce's school.
    - Brooks,Julia M.C.(Mrs.), 1897 (Folder 5)
      Two letters from Mrs. Julia M.C. Brooks. One letter to Mary Phelps dated Hartford (Conn.) [1897 Aug] concerning her mother, Mary Bassett's, attendance at Miss Pierce's School. The second letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated Hartford (Conn.) [no year] Oct 7 regretting that she has no information about her mother's life at Miss Pierce's School
    - Butler,Emily (Folder 6)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated from Fox Meadow, Scarsdale (N.Y.) [no year] Sep 11.
    - Child, Elizabeth P, 1895-1896 (Folder 7)
      3 Letters to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel
    - Clephane, Anne M (Mrs. Lewis), 1907 Sep 12 (Folder 8)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel
    - Copp, Catherine B (Mrs. John J), 1897 (Folder 9)
      2 Letters to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel
    - Copp, John J, 1897 Dec 15 (Folder 10)
    - Curtis, Emily C, 1897-1898 (Folder 11)
      Letters to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel
    - Curtis, Emily C, 1902 (Folder 12)
      5 letters to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel
    - dePeyster, Frederic (Folder 13)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel with information about Eliza Ann S. dePeyster, a student at Miss Pierce's School.
    - Dowd, W. F., 1902 Aug 22 (Folder 14)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel with information about Mrs. Lucretia Buell, a pupil of Miss Pierce's school.
    - Farnsworth, Henry A, 1897 (Folder 15)
      2 letters to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel replying to ENV inquiry about pupils at Miss Pierce's school.
    - Gardiner, Sarah D, 1896 Dec 20 (Folder 16)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel. Information abour her grandmothers, Sarah D. Gardiner and Julienne MacLachlan who were pupils at Miss Pierce's.
    - Gould, [ ] Vail, Mrs. (Folder 17)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated Washington, [no year] March 15.
    - Gray, Jane (Loring), Mrs. Asa, 1900 Jan 31 (Folder 18)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel, includes a letter to Mrs. Gray from Julia T. Noyes, dated Litchfield (Conn.) 1863 Oct 12.
    - Gray, Jane (Loring), Mrs. Asa, 1895-1902 (Folder 19)
    - Gray, Jane (Loring), Mrs. Asa, 1899-1902 (Folder 20)
      Letters to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel concerning research for Miss PIerce's School; information about Pierce family, and other news.
    - H [ ], Kate E, 1896 Nov 4 (Folder 21)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel from Stamford (Conn.)
    - Hinsdale, Horace G, 1898 May 3 (Folder 22)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated Lakewood (NJ)
    - Hoppin, Mary D, 1898 Jan 21 (Folder 23)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel includes a letter from Ann S Farnam (Mrs. Henry) formerly Ann Whitman, to Mrs. Hoppin
    - Hunt, Mary A, 1902 Feb 14 (Folder 24)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel with memories of her days at Litchfield & Miss Pierce's School.
    - Jackson, Joseph, Mrs. (Folder 25)
      Notes about pupils at LFA and their married names.
    - Kingsbury, Frederick J, 1898-1901 (Folder 26)
      4 letters to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel
    - Knapp, Laura B (Folder 27)
      Letter to Elizabeth Barney Buel
    - Knight, Caroline Sedgwick, 1902 Mar 31 (Folder 28)
      Letter to Elizabeth Barney Buel dated Sharon (Conn.)
    - Lincoln, Jeanie Gould, 1897 Feb 22 (Folder 29)
    - Logan, Conrad (Folder 30)
    - Lord, Fanny, 1899 Nov 11 (Folder 31)
      Memories of Litchfield Female Academy
    - Lord, Katharine M, 1897 Nov 1 (Folder 32)
    - Loring, Katharine P (Folder 33)
    - Lyman, Mary E, 1914 Jul 7 (Folder 34)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel with photography of an embroidery by Esther Lyman who attended LFA
    - Marsh, Fanny A, 1897, 1902 (Folder 35)
      2 letters to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel
    - Newcomb, Lydia B, 1902 Jan 6 (Folder 36)
      Letter to Elizabeth Barney Buel dated New Haven (Conn.)
    - Peck, Frances S, 1897 May 7 (Folder 37)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated Arlington (NJ)
    - Perkins, J. Deming, 1897-1898 (Folder 38)
    - Perkins, Lucy A, 1897 Feb 17 (Folder 39)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated Boston (Mass.)
    - Phelps, M.L. (Folder 40)
    - Pierce family genealogy part 1' (Folder 41)
      Information about the Pierce family collected by Emily Noyes Vanderpoel.
    - Pierce family genealogy part 2 (Folder 42)
      Information collected by Emily Noyes Vanderpoel.
    - Pierce family genealogy part 3 (Folder 43)
    - Pierce family genealogy part 4 (Folder 44)
    - Pierce, Sarah (Folder 45)
      Letter to Thomas & Ruth (Pierce) Croswell dated [1830] Sep 5
    - Preston, Cornelius (Folder 46)
    - Richards, Anna M, 1902 May 13 (Folder 47)
    - Sears, Anna, 1907 Mar 25 (Folder 48)
    - Seelye, Ann Eliza (Jackson), Mrs.George C., 1897 May 14 (Folder 49)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated Geneva (NY)
    - Skinner, Mary B, 1897 May 14 (Folder 50)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated Yonkers (NY)
    - Spencer, Susan, 1898 Feb 16 (Folder 51)
      Letter to Mr. Kingsbury
    - Stone, Mason S, 1901 Mar 14 (Folder 52)
    - Strong, J. P., 1898 Feb 15 (Folder 53)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated Yale Univ.
    - Thompson, Esther H, 1897, 1902 (Folder 54)
    - Thompson, George E, 1927 Mar 5 (Folder 55)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel includes memories of early Litchfield and some mention of Miss Pierce's School.
    - Treat, Julia Hubbell (Folder 56)
    - Vanderpoel, Emily Noyes (Folder 57)
      Notes for "Chronicles of a Pioneer School"
    - Vanderpoel, Emily Noyes (Folder 58)
      Post card reproduction by Benedict, Litchfield, Conn. from a sketch of of the Litchfield Female Academy by Emily Noyes Vanderpoel.
    - Wallbridge, Margaret E (Folder 59)
    - Warner, Harriet E, 1902 (Folder 60)
      2 letters to Elizabeth Barney Buel
    - Webb, Z.S., 1898 Oct 3 (Folder 61)
      Letter to Emily Noyes Vanderpoel dated New York City.
    - Whittelsay, Joseph, 1899 Feb 26 (Folder 62)
    - Catlin, James P, 1933 Dec. 26 (Folder 63)
      Letter dated New Haven, Conn. to Mrs. E.C. Barney Buel with details of his father John Catlin as principal at Miss Pierce's and his teaching career.
    - Catlin, James, 1934 Sep 12 (Folder 64)
      Letter dated New Haven, Conn. to Mrs. Emily N. Vanderpoel with information about his father John Catlin as a pupil at Litchfield Female Academy, his family & marriage, and teaching.
    - "Chronicles of a Pioneer School", 1903
      An incomplete set of the original plates used for the illustrations in Emily Noyes Vanderpoel's "Chronicles of a Pioneer School."
    - "Chronicles of a Pioneer School", 1903-1906
      A scrapbook collected by Emily Noyes Vanderpoel of newspaper clippings, letters, comments, information & bills from the publisher, etc. relating to the publishing of her book "Chronicles of a Pioneer School."
  - Vanderpoel Family Papers
    - Boyce, Henry and Octavia, 1851 Dec 24 (Folder 1)
      Mr. & Mrs. Boyce of Rapides, Louisiana appoinat James McBride their attorney to collect money from a suit over some real estate in New York City, in which James Clemes & his wife Eliza are
      complaintants and Bryan Mullanphy and the Boyces are defendents. Payments made by Aaron Vanderpoel.
    - Clemens, James, Jr. & Eliza, 1851 Dec 2 (Folder 2)
      The Clemens appoint George W Thatcher as their attorney in a suit to collect money for real estate in New York City from Henry & Octavia Boyce. Aaron Vanderpoel receives payments.
    - Curtis, William E, 1876 (Folder 3)
      Two letters (Sept. 1 & Sept. 15) to Julia F. Noyes (Mrs. William Curtis Noyes) dated Watertown (Conn.) regarding a visit by members of the 2nd Conn. Heavy Artillery and William Curtis' remarks to them. Includes a copy of the Waterbury Daily American newspaper Sept 14, 1876 with a report on the reunion.
    - Gigliardi, Giovanni e Figlio, 1856 Dec 18 (Folder 4)
      Bill from Gigliardi in Florence, Italy to Mrs. Arendt Vanderpoel for purchase of copies of 4 religious paintings.
    - May, William L, 1837 Feb 7 (Folder 5)
      Deed to Aaron Vanderpoel for land in Chicago, Cook County, Illinois.
    - McBride, George, 1850 (Folder 6)
      Two letters sent from Dublin, 1850 Jul 30 and 1850 Aug 2 to George's brother James McBride in New York with general news of business and family.
    - Noyes, Julia F, 1876 (Folder 7)
      Two letters, 1876 Sep 2 and 1876 Sep 28 to William E. Curtis in reply to his letters regarding the reunion of the 2nd Conn. Heavy Artillery on Sep 13.
    - Vanderpoel, Ellen McBride, 1848 Feb 7 (Folder 8)
      List of pieces in dinner & dessert set given to her by her father.
    - Vanderpoel, Emily Noyes (Folder 9)
      Photographs of Mrs. Vanderpoel's studio in New York City.